Helen Leland Witmer Papers, 1928-1979
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Helen Leland Witmer papers
1928-1979
1935-1965
Witmer, Helen Leland
MS 199
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Sociologist, teacher, and social worker. The bulk of the Witmer papers pertain to her writings, including notes, typescripts and manuscripts for her unpublished book, Juvenile Delinquents in Court: A Study in Four Countries (Israel, Poland, Puerto Rico and Yugoslavia). There are also photographs, correspondence, lectures, and conference papers. Also documented are her tenure as director of research at Smith College School for Social Work and at the U.S. Children's Bureau.
Helen Leland Witmer was born in Lansford, Pennsylvania. She earned her B.A. from Dickinson College in 1919, and her M.A. from the University of Wisconsin in 1923. She did post doctoral work at the London School of Economics and went on to receive a certificate of social work from Bryn Mawr College in 1924.
After working as a high school teacher in Pennsylvania, a statistician in the Massachusetts Division of Corrections, and as Assistant Professor of Sociology at the University of Minnesota, she became Director of Research at the Smith College School for Social Work where she remained from 1929 to 1949. Her responsibilities at Smith included formulating final exam questions, helping to set standards for social work theses, editing Smith College Studies in Social Work, and conducting research and writing for various state and national social service and mental health agencies. From 1949 to 1951, she was Director of Fact-finding for the White House Conference on Children and Youth. In 1951 Witmer became Director of Research for the United States Children's Bureau (a Health, Education and Welfare agency), a position she held from 1951 until 1967. During her tenure there, she worked on setting research standards for evaluating federally funded children's programs. She also wrote and published extensively on such topics as juvenile delinquency, pediatric psychiatry, family welfare, daycare, parent education, adoption, and child guidance. In 1967 she became editor of the Children's Bureau Research Reports, a publication of Children's Bureau research findings.
The papers are arranged in three series: Biographical Material, Writings, and Professional Activities. The Biographical Material series contains curriculum vitae, photographs and memorabilia. The bulk of the Writings series is comprised of notes and a book-length typescript for Juvenile Delinquents in Court: A Study in Four Countries, an examination of the management of juvenile delinquency in selected cities in Israel, Poland, Puerto Rico and Yugoslavia. Although the book was ready to go to press, it appears that Witmer never found a publisher. This series also contains typescripts of essays, lecture and conference papers, and journal articles.
The Professional Activities series contains correspondence, typescripts, and notes from Witmer's tenure at the Smith College School for Social Work. There are also extensive notes pertaining to her work at the United States Children's Bureau.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Writings
III. Professional Activities
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The family of Helen Leland Witmer donated her papers to the Smith College School for Social Work in 1980. They were transferred to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1982, via Vida S. Grayson. A subsequent donation was made by Charles Gershenson in 1987.
Search Terms
Child welfare--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Juvenile delinquency--United States--History--Sources; Mental health services--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Smith College. School for Social Work--Faculty--History; Witmer, Helen Leland
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
  - Curriculum vitae, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1950, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memorabilia, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SERIES II. WRITINGS
  - Book
    - Juvenile Delinquents in Court: A Study in Four Countries (unpublished), circa 1966
      - Summary of project (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Typescripts and notes, Ch. 1-9 (Box 1, Folder 5-22)
      - Typescripts and notes, Ch. 10-11 and appendix (Box 2, Folder 23-32)
  - Essays
    - Typescript, "Science and Social Work," undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Other typescripts, 1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Journal articles, 1933-35 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Lectures and conference papers, 1935-61 (Box 2, Folder 36-44)
  - Lectures and conference papers, A-W, undated (Box 3, Folder 45-51)
  - Humorous, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Smith College School for Social Work
    - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Tests and exams, 1936-48, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Notes on writing and evaluating theses, 1937-47, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - "Periodicals, Indices and Encyclopedias" (compiled by students), 1945 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Annual Meeting of the Schools of Social Work: correspondence, agenda, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Mid-Century White House Conference on Children and Youth: newspaper clipping, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - United States Children's Bureau
    - Ribicoff Bill: memoranda, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Evaluation research project
      - Prospectus, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Correspondence, 1955-58 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Abstracts, 1952-55, undated (Box 3, Folder 62-63)
      - Typescript and manuscript drafts, Chapter 1 and unidentified, circa 1955-56 (Box 3, Folder 64-65)
      - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 66-67)
      - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 68-70)
      - Bibliography, undated (Box 4, Folder 71-72)